<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The behaviour of Edward Kirk after his condemnation for murdering his wife with the advice and prayers which he left with the ordinary, desiring him to publish the same for the reclaiming of vicious youth : together vvith the behaviour of the other condemned malefactors in Newgate.</title>
            <author>Smith, Samuel, 1620-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60547</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10200</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13777254</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13777254</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101764</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60547)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101764)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 850:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The behaviour of Edward Kirk after his condemnation for murdering his wife with the advice and prayers which he left with the ordinary, desiring him to publish the same for the reclaiming of vicious youth : together vvith the behaviour of the other condemned malefactors in Newgate.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Samuel, 1620-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Geo. Croom ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Samuel Smith.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kirk, Edmund, d. 1684.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:101764:1"/>
            <head>THE BEHAVIOUR OF <hi>Edward Kirk,</hi> After his CONDEMNATION FOR Murdering his Wife; WITH THE Advice and Prayers which he left with the Ordinary, deſiring him to Publiſh the ſame for the Reclaiming OF Vicious Youth. TOGETHER VVith the Behaviour of the other Condemned Malefactors in <hi>NEWGATE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHEREAS at the late Seſſions of Gaol-Delivery held in the <hi>Old-Bayly</hi> on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> and <hi>Thurſday,</hi> the 2d. and 3d. Days of <hi>July,</hi> 1684. Nine Perſons received Sentence of Death, <hi>viz. Edward Kirk, John Mould, John Holtam, John Bennet, John Richardſon, James Walden, Mary Shelton, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Hill,</hi> and <hi>Morgan Reading.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now whereas ſeveral Malefactors Condemned to Dye, do in the Priſon of <hi>Newgate,</hi> deſire the Ordinary to Publiſh their Conferrences with him, thereby giving an Account of their Penitency; and to warn others by their Example of ſuffering Juſtice, to avoid the ſame Crimes. The Ordinary thereupon thinks it a neceſſary Service to give a faithful Account of the ſaid Condemned Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors Behaviour; hopeing thereby it will be a means to reclam Vice in Youth.</p>
            <p>This account therefore he now gives, that on the next Day after Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation (they all appeared together in the Chappel) where they were Exhorted and Prayed with; the like was done on <hi>Saturday.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101764:2"/>
            <p>On the Lords Day, following being the 6th. of <hi>July</hi> Inſtant thoſe for whoſe Execution the Warrant was directed, were at the Chappel; where the Ordinary Preached on this Text, <hi>viz.</hi> the 33. Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Ezek.</hi> and the 11th. Verſe. <hi>Say unto them, as I Live, ſaieth the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the Death of the Wicked, but that the Wicked turn from his way and Live: Turn ye turn ye from your Evil Ways, for why will ye Dye, O Houſe of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>The Ordinary obſerved, that <hi>Edward Kirk</hi> who was Convicted for the Murder of <hi>Joan Kirk</hi> his Wife, in cutting her <hi>Throat</hi> on <hi>Sunday,</hi> the 25th. Day of <hi>May</hi> laſt, in the <hi>Fields</hi> near <hi>Paddington,</hi> whom he often Viſited before his Tryal; ſeemed then to be more affected with his Horrid Crime, then was obſerved before, and ſince continues ſo.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="text">
                        <head>The Paper of Advice which <hi>Edward Kirk,</hi> left with the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in Priſon.</head>
                        <p>WHereas, the All-ſearching Eye of God with whom Darkneſs is Light, and by whom the moſt Hidden and Secret Things are made Manifeſt, has made a juſt Diſcovery of my Tranſcendent Wickedneſs; I think it equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my Duty to God and Man, to ſecond it with a Penitent Confeſſion, that ſo the dear Intereſt which the Meritorious Death and Paſſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for the Sins of frail Man-kind may be applicable to my ſelf: For ſuch is the Miſery and weight of Sin I lie under, that unleſs the Miraculous Grace and Mercy of my Creator interpoſe, is ſufficient to preſs me down to the neather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Hell.</hi> Upon this Conſideration, I eſteem it my Duty to Publiſh to the World the occaſion which had the influence on my Puniſhment, or what is the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious cauſe of my Fatal and untimely End. The occaſion was ſo ſlender, that it rather aggravates my cruel Crime, than mittigates it. My Wife for whoſe Murder I duly ſuffer was of that Temper, that ſhe was indefatigably officious to hunt me from Place to Place; but whether out of Love or Neceſſity ſhe did it, is a difficulty to Diſcern, and therefore I proclaim her Innocent; and dare impute nothing to my Excuſe, my Paſſion being above my Principle; and that Grace of God which ſhould lead Men to a true and ſincere Repentance, for want of a true management of it, was taken away from me, and I left, like the <hi>Jews,</hi> in my own Willfulneſs and Stubbornneſs, to act whatever my Spiritual Enemy the <hi>Devil</hi> could impoſe upon my Inclination: and indeed the influence of my Wickedneſs is ſuch, that if I had the Greateſt affluence of Sublunary Enjoyments, it inbitters the moſt hopeful paſſages of my Life; and nothing can be Sweet and Cordial to me but the precious Blood of <hi>Christ,</hi> which was ſhed for the Sins of the Penitent; ſuch likewiſe is the preſent Puniſhment of the Murder; that through the ſenſe of it, I am Involved into a Deluge of Melancholy, ſometimes preventing my addreſs to God for aſſurance of Pardon: yet according to that Gracious Light which it pleaſeth God to intruſt me with, I continually lie under the conteſt of Sin and <hi>Satan,</hi> and heartily beg for that Supernal Regeneration, which is a turning from Darkneſs to Light, and from the power of <hi>Satan,</hi> to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. Now, becauſe the world is more Govern'd by Example than Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, I am highly and zealouſly concerned to propoſe the reflection of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to all thoſe who are miſerably biaſed to a Diſſolute and un-Chriſtian Life; that from my doleful End, they may be cautioned to diſcard all ſuch Ways as may be Effectual to draw them on to <hi>Perdition,</hi> and living without God in the World.</p>
                        <p>Nor can I forbear to expreſs my Inclination, which was always equal to the Natural State of all Men: yet ſuch was my Misfortune, that I added the Whip and Spur to make it Strong and Vigorous, and was as inquiſitive to know Lewd Company as ready to Imbrace whatſoever was adapted to Irregularity, the Sin of breaking the <hi>Sabbath</hi> I cannot paſs by, and was continually Guilty of: upon which Holy Day I committed the Heinous Sin of Murder; while Pride, Luſt and Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury, had the ſole Dominion over me, and was frequently more acceptable than any thing of Piety and Godlineſs: Thus my Soul being ſurfeited with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Sin, I am brought to condign Puniſhment. Take timely care therefore
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101764:2"/>all Young Men, how you are drawn in by the Bewitching Luſt and Love of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: for tho my Relations were Reſponſable, and gave me a Good and Pious Education, yet the Grace of God which is infinitly eligible before the whole World, was wanting in me, and juſtly left me to the Guilt of Murder. Let no Man therefore truſt in uncertain Riches, nor bolſter himſelf up with the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of his Friends, in order to any hopes of Security from ſuffering the juſt Puniſhment of an evil Life; for there is a juſt God that made and Governs the World, who will not only in this World, but in that which is to come, Shower down <hi>Hail, Fire,</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone</hi> on thoſe who tread under Foot the Son of God, and put him to open Shame. If this Confeſſion and Advice have efficacy to reclaim any, it only gains the end for which I deſign'd it, and to God above be Glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>Two Prayers which <hi>Edward Kirk,</hi> deſired might be Printed with his Advice to Youth.</head>
                           <p>O <hi>Lord God, Good and Gracious, Everlaſting and Bleſſed God; I muſt confeſs I have been a great Sinner, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy Pardon am utterly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndon for Ever: and therefore I pray thee Lord, that thou wouldeſt be pleaſed to waſh away all my Sins from my Heart, and give me a new Spirit within, ſo that I may truly ſerve thee in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, thoſe few Minutes that I have to live in this World: that when my Soul and Body parts, my Soul may aſcend up into Heaven, to God on High: ſo that he that ſhed his Precious Blood for Sinners (if it be his Bleſſed Will) may make my Peace with God. Of all my Sins that I have Committed, there is none ſo ſad and Horrible as the Sin of Murder is: therefore I Beſeech thee O Lord, to blot out that loud crying Sin from before thy Preſence, ſo that it may not riſe up in Judgment againſt me, when I come before thy Tribunal-Seat on High.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>Oh! that men would conſider this in time, that Sin will one Day change their Countenance; however it cometh in a flattering form, pretending nothing but Friendſhip but in the end, will leave a Sting behind it, even a guilty Conſcience, Terror of Mind, and anguiſh of Spirit; wherefore let us flye from Sin, as from the biting of a <hi>Serpent,</hi> that we be not ſtung to Death; knowing that the ways of Sin, is Death.</p>
                           <p>O <hi>Lord moſt Holy, Good and Gracious, Everlaſting and Bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lord God, how Glorious art thou Lord thou art a great and a Merciful God; and thou haſt done more for me a thouſand times than I have deſerved; I confeſs I have been a great Sinner;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101764:3"/>I have done thoſe things which I ſhould not have done, and I have left undone thoſe things which I ſhould have done. Lord help me, and ſtrengthen my Faith every Minute more and more, thoſe few Minutes that I have to live in this World, that when I am depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hence, through the merits of Jeſus Chriſt, I may aſcend into a Heavenly Kingdom,</hi> Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward Kirk,</hi> acknowledged that he was at the Execution of <hi>John Gower,</hi> a Coach-maker, who for Murdering his Wife, was Executed at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> on the 23d. of <hi>May</hi> laſt; 1684. And that after <hi>Kirk</hi> returned from <hi>Tyburn, Satan</hi> ſuggeſted him to Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own Wife within one hour after; That he Prayed againſt the Temptation; yet, not ſo fervently as he ought. The Inſtigation came with Violence upon him, about ſix a Clock on the Lords Day in the Morning, being the 25th. of <hi>May,</hi> 1684. That he then contrived how to draw her out in the After-noon to walk with him into the <hi>Fields;</hi> That when he got her out, he ſometimes went before her, and called to her to walk faſter after him: and when they were near <hi>Paddington,</hi> he told the Ordinary, that he pretended ſome excuſe into a <hi>Gravel-Pit,</hi> which was within two <hi>Fields</hi> of <hi>Tyburn;</hi> That he asked his Wife to give him her Hand, which ſhe did; and ſo led her into the <hi>Gravel Pit.</hi> That when ſhe was there, he Quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with her, and Bruiſed her Face and Head with a <hi>Cane;</hi> that ſhe begged him to ſpare her, but he drew out a <hi>Knife</hi> to cut her <hi>Throat:</hi> which he attempting to do, ſhe Strugled with him, uſing theſe Words, <hi>Lord have Mercy on my Soul, Was ever Woman ſo, barbarouſly Murdered?</hi> After he had cut her <hi>Throat,</hi> and returned home, he endeavoured as much as he could to compoſe his Countenance, and go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his Buſineſs, and ſo order his Behaviour, that nothing more than ordinary might appear in his Looks, to give ſuſpition that he had been about any un-Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, much leſs ſo Horrid a Fact. He told the Ordinary that he would at his Tryal Plead Guilty, and beg God and the Kings Mercy; yet againſt his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution he denied the Fact, till it was proved upon him, by his own Confeſſion before his Tryal. Notwithſtanding he uſed many falſe Stories to evade the Proof of the Fact, as appears in the account of his Tryal. Since his Condemnation to Death he hath plainly Bewailed his great prevarication and falſe aſſeverationtos the Court of Judicature; hoping that by Repentance and through a true lively Faith, in the Meritorious ſatisfaction of Chriſts Blood-ſhed; His Horrid Murder, and the denial of it ſo Impudently in the Court of Juſtice, will be pardoned by God, to him. And the Ordinary, doth hope that upon narrow ſearch into the frame of his Heart, that <hi>Edward Kirk,</hi> had ſome Ground to Expect a happy Eternity, for he ſaid that his Sin was ſo great that he deſerved to Dye; and deſired not to Live.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Andrew Hill,</hi> Aged 21 Years, acknowledged to the Ordinary in conference, that he had ſpent his time very Idly, and lived a very diſorderly Life, often quenching the motions of the Holy Spirit: and warns all Young-Men to mind their Honeſt Imployments, and not to ſeek out, nor mix with Lewd Company, leaſt they come to an untimely Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Morgan Reading,</hi> Condemned for a Burglary, was very ſenſible of his Sinful courſe of Life; and grieved that he had commited ſeveral Impieties againſt clear and ſtrong Convictions in Conſcience to the Contrary.</p>
            <p>Another of the Condemned Perſons, being a Luſty and Comely Perſon, of the Age of Four and twenty Years, is very Penitent, and much bewailed his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Precious Time, neglecting the publick Aſſemblies on the Lords Day, and the duty of Prayer, whereby he fell under the Temptations of <hi>Satan</hi> and bad Company; ſo that he commited many Exceſſes, ſuch as he deſires all Young-Men to refrain from, particularly to bridle their Tongues from Curſing and Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or uſeing any other Intemperance; for God in due time will diſcover all who perſiſt in Impenitency.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated on <date>
                     <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 10th. Day of <hi>July,</hi> 1684.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Samuel Smith,</hi> Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Geo. Croom,</hi> in <hi>Thdmes-ſtreet;</hi> over againſt <hi>Baynard</hi>'s <hi>Caſtle,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
